[Music]
consider a semi-circle and then along
the diameter of the semicircle draw two
smaller tangent semicircles the Shaded
region shown here lying inside the
larger semicircle and outside the
smaller semicircle is called an arbolos
the term arbolos literally means
shoemaker's knife by varying the sizes
of the inner two semicircles we get
various different arbolo shapes all
lying inside the same outer semicircle
here's an amazing theorem about the area
of the arbolos consider the semi chord
from the tangent point of the circles to
the larger semicircle and consider this
circle that has that semicord as its
diameter as we vary the sizes of the
inner semicircles we see that this new
circle's area changes just like the
arbolos area changes the amazing
principle here is that the area of the
arbolos is actually equal to the area of
that Circle that has the semi chord as
its diameter let's see a visual proof
justifying this fact
first let's complete the semicircle so
that it's now a full circle and then
rotate the semi chord down to this
bottom semicircle we can use this
semi-cord to create this triangle which
happens to be a right angled triangle by
thales triangle theorem next we can
decompose this right triangle into these
two smaller right triangles and split
the diagram into three separate pieces
one for each of the right triangles
for each one of these triangles we'll
draw semicircles off the three sides of
the triangle like this
according to the Pythagorean theorem the
sum of the areas of the semicircles off
the legs of the right triangle must be
equal to the area of the semicircle off
the hypotenuse of the right triangle so
in each of these diagrams the blue area
is equal to the pink area but now we can
glue these three diagrams back together
one at a time remembering that pink
areas in blue areas counteract one
another when we do that we see that the
only area surviving is the pink area of
the arbolos and the Blue Area
corresponding to the circle whose
diameter is the semicord but remember
that the sum of the blue areas was equal
to the sum of the pink areas and
therefore the area of the arbolos is in
fact equal to the area of the pictured
Circle no matter how we drew this
diagram thales triangle theorem would
hold for the semi chord in question and
so the area of the arbolos is always
equal to the area of the related Circle